<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The French politician found out, or, Considerations on the late pretensions that France claims to England and Ireland and her designs and plots in order thereunto by a well-wisher of his countrey.</title>
            <author>Well-wisher of his countrey.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40465</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2194</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9405</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13743901</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13743901</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101687</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40465)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101687)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 454:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The French politician found out, or, Considerations on the late pretensions that France claims to England and Ireland and her designs and plots in order thereunto by a well-wisher of his countrey.</title>
                  <author>Well-wisher of his countrey.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28, 23 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Harford ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisements on p. 23 at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101687:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101687:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE French Politician FOUND OUT, OR CONSIDERATIONS On the Late Pretenſions That <hi>FRANCE</hi> Claims to <hi>ENGLAND</hi> and <hi>IRELAND;</hi> and her DESIGNS and PLOTS in Order thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Well-wisher of his Countrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Harford,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> M.DC.LXXX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:101687:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101687:2"/>
            <head>THE French Politician Found Out.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE FIRST DISCOURSE.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>RIbier, Du Chaſtelet,</hi> The Author of the <hi>French Politician,</hi> and other <hi>Libellers</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> have had the Confidence of late to pour out ſuch a torrent of Injuries, ſhallow Pretenſions, and Titles to <hi>England,</hi> that a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject long acquainted with their Ways, thought himſelf bound in Duty and Faithfulneſs to his King and Countrey, humbly to lay ſome of his Obſervations before them; whereby it may
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101687:3"/>poſſibly appear, that <hi>France</hi> is not ſo much our Friend as ſhe of late pretended: That theſe Pretenſions of hers are not the meer Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demick Notions of ſome private Speculatiſt, but the ſenſe of their Rulers; that they do but watch their Opportunity to put theſe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Claims into Execution againſt us. And therefore if this be in ſome manner made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that we can never have a fitter op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity than now to be before-hand with them, in entring into a Confederacy and Arms, if need be, with our Neighbours, againſt theſe Common Enemies, leaſt when they have too much weakened the reſt, they become too ſtrong for us alone, eſpecially at Sea.</p>
               <p>Let's then obſerve, That it hath been of late a Practice of <hi>France,</hi> to make uſe of ſuch Title-Broachers, as her Trumpets and Heraulds, a little before ſhe's reſolved to invade any Countrey, to publiſh ſome Right, forſooth, to thoſe Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions whom next ſhe intends to ſet upon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Right and Reaſon, thereby to raiſe the Valour of her own Men with the ſpeciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Juſtice in their Vndertaking; to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the Minds and Reſolutions of ſome on the future Enemies ſide: to ſuſpend alſo the hands of her Neighbours, from intermeddling in a Quarrel which ſeems ſo plauſible, or at leaſt ſo doubtful; and that ſurely <hi>France</hi> (think they)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101687:3"/>cannot be unjuſt or raſh in Actions, whereof ſhe is ready to give ſuch a fair Accompt to the World before-hand: And it is Prudence firſt to ſee what her Adverſaries will anſwer her; ſo ſay they. And thus <hi>France</hi> leaving the Matter dormant, for a while, as if ſhe thought no more of it; before, or as ſoon as her Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Party makes an Anſwer to her <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſto,</hi> ſhe ſuddenly and unexpectedly comes and makes her Reply with her Sword; there's that ſhe would be at, from the very beginning; let your Defence to her claim be never ſo ſtrong and juſt. Tuſh! that was but an Amuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and her <hi>Inter Arma ſilent Leges,</hi> ſcorns to be bawked with ſuch Ponctilio's.</p>
               <p>All obſerving Perſons might be furniſhed with Proofs enough of this Maxime, in the late Conduct of <hi>France</hi> toward her Neighbours; but here are ſome whereof I had a nearer occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion than many to know the particulars.</p>
               <p>Cardinal <hi>Richelieu,</hi> who as it is known firſt laid the Deſign of making his Maſter the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Monarch of all Chriſtendom, before he attackt <hi>Spain;</hi> in order thereunto encourages <hi>Caſſan</hi> to write his Book of the <hi>Pretenſions</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> upon all or moſt of the Kingdoms and Principalities of <hi>Europe;</hi> which he goes about to prove of each one in particular, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101687:4"/>by former Conqueſt, by Alliances and Succeſſions, by Clauſes in Treaties, and ſuch other obſolete Titles. However this Pretenſion Writer ſo tickled the French Ambition, and gave ſuch ſeeming Colours to thoſe Deſigns they would be upon otherwiſe, had they no ground at all; that the Cardinal ordered a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Sixteen thouſand Livers to be given to that Author; and ſo ſent his Generals to go and purſue with the Sword theſe goodly Claims and forgotten Inheritance of the French Kings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arroy, Du Puy, D' Aubery,</hi> and others, had no worſe recompence, and were ſet on before theſe late Wars againſt <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Flanders;</hi> for to forge Titles to theſe Countries their Maſter had with himſelf determined to invade. They have done it however, but were ſmartly anſwered by <hi>Liſola</hi> and <hi>Ramos;</hi> and though Monſieur <hi>D' Ambrun</hi> bragg'd then at <hi>Madrid,</hi> that <hi>Ramos</hi> was the only Man <hi>Spain</hi> had to maintain its Intereſt upon the point of the Devolution; but that the King of <hi>France</hi> could make out his Right at the Head of Sixty thouſand Lawyers; yet his Maſter ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſtand to make good this French Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conade, rather choſe to ſpeak at the Head of more than Sixty thouſand Armed Men: While his Ambaſſadors were thus drolling and cajolling
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101687:4"/>with their unwary Neighbours; and Amuſing them with fair Pretences and Promiſes of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their Right by Lawyers and Mediators. But alas! with <hi>France</hi> it is too ſcrupulous a Nicety, ſo to depend on the Deciſions at the Bar, or on thoſe at <hi>Munſter, Breda,</hi> or <hi>Nimeguen</hi> either; her King will plead his Rights but with the Mouths of his Cannons bravely, <hi>Alexander</hi> like; and he's told he hath more Right to all <hi>Europe</hi> than this Young <hi>Grecian</hi> had to <hi>Aſia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>Patru</hi> in his New Law Book left this on Record as a perpetual Maxime to be followed by <hi>France,</hi> which he oft before maintained in open Parliament, <hi>That the Word</hi> Kingdom, <hi>with them, doth comprehend generally all the Lands, Principalities, and Dominions, which Fontune, Succeſs and the Valour of the French Monarchs, can add to the Sacred Subjection of the</hi> Flower de Luce. <hi>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> Rivers <hi>and</hi> Rivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, <hi>by entring into the Sea, loſe themſelves preſently, with all their particular qualities, as ſoon as they are incorporated to the Noble Ocean, ſo all conquered Provinces and Nations, do loſe their peculiar Names, Priviledges, and Prerogatives, to be made Members of the Firſt Monarchy of the VVorld, and of its Laws and Priviledges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pray tell me where this Maxime will not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101687:5"/>reach, or be made to ſtretch rather. For as the Habit in any unjuſt Courſe will mortifie the remorſe, and check the Senſe of all other Law, that may dictate the contrary; ſo <hi>France,</hi> by a long practice of following theſe boundleſs Maximes, is become as it were accuſtomed to think that her Conqueſts muſt be as large as her Ambition; and that thoſe Nations do really belong to her, ſhe and her Mercenary Pens had but a Fancy of Right unto in the beginning.</p>
               <p>But what of all this, you'll ſay; theſe are but general Preſumptions and Jealouſies, when <hi>France</hi> puts in no Claim againſt <hi>England;</hi> I never heard of any, I can't fancy which way. Then hear further:</p>
               <p>The fore-mentioned <hi>Ribier</hi> (among the reſt) ſets out this Title of <hi>France</hi> to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Crown, as you may more fully ſee in his French Book, and in the following Diſcourſe; And one is in right of the Dolphin <hi>Lewis,</hi> Son to <hi>Philip Auguſtus,</hi> who by the Popes means, and of ſome of the Rebelling Lords, entred and was Crowned here in <hi>England,</hi> and ravaged here a good while; deſigning by a general Maſſacre of all the Engliſh Princes and Peers to ſhorten his Conqueſt: till one of his French Cabinet Councellors could not die quietly till he revealed this horrible Project to ſome of the Engliſh Nobility. Such a Right
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101687:5"/>as this, with ſuch other, the French Kings are put in Remembrance of in their Coronation Oath.</p>
               <p>Such another Claim they lay to <hi>Scotland</hi> in Right of <hi>Francis</hi> the Second, who married <hi>Mary Steward</hi> Queen of <hi>Scotland;</hi> and though ſhe had no iſſue by him, yet 'tis a Maxime with them, That the Crown can loſe none of the Rights it once had, and that no Aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can be made from it, but it ſtill Reinters.</p>
               <p>By a Sequel of the ſame Maxime, they go on and ſay, That <hi>Eccleſia eſt ſicut Minor.</hi> That no Aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can be made from the Church no more than from <hi>Minors.</hi> But <hi>Ireland</hi> belong'd to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to which the Natives gave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves up long ago; now the French King is Eldeſt Son of the Church, and her Heir: Nay it's ſaid, tha this good Old Mother either ſold or gave him that Kingdom, when ſhe could make no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it her ſelf; and may he not then claim it upon as good and better Grounds than <hi>Spain</hi> took and kept <hi>Navarr</hi> from its Lawful King, being an Heretick; of which that Wiſe Granam deprived him by no other Right then by that by which ſhe pretends to diſpoſeſs Heretick Kings.</p>
               <p>It was by that Right ſhe ſent her Nuncio to diſplay the Banner of Rebellion in <hi>Ireland</hi> in 41, and another Nuncio in or about 78, to raiſe the ſame Tragedy. Was it not by this Tranſport
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101687:6"/>or making over of <hi>Ireland</hi> to her moſt Chriſtian Son, that the Titular Biſhop <hi>Talbot,</hi> undertook with others in Seventy three to prepare a Sea-Port Town in <hi>Ireland</hi> by <hi>Brthe</hi> or <hi>Stratagem</hi> to Receive a French Army, and to have <hi>Iriſh</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough ſecretly enliſted in a readineſs to meet them; when they Attempted firſt to Kill the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Agent, who came to diſcloſe their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and prevailed with Secretary <hi>Perridge</hi> and others to Poſt after him; <hi>Swearing, That if they met</hi> Everard, <hi>he would never come to</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>to tell Tales;</hi> as even Sir <hi>Edward Hunger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, who chanc'd to meet them remembers.</hi> When upon another ſham Accuſation they thought they had procured his Mouth to be for ever ſtopt in the Tower, then I ſay they went on ſtill with their Deſign in Favour of <hi>France;</hi> and ſome others, unknown to the former, who ſince deſerted their Camps, diſcloſed that the ſaid <hi>Talbot</hi> and others, were in 78, carrying on the ſame Treachery as ſecurely as before: And ſome, even in this very Month, came from <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Accuſed, as is ſaid, before the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, thoſe very Perſons, with other Titular French Agents, as <hi>Plunkett, Molony,</hi> &amp;c. of which ſome were, as it is known, in great Favour and Correſpondency with the French Court.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſed the <hi>French,</hi> had with the Papiſts conceived ſuch a Deſign on <hi>England</hi> or <hi>Ireland,</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101687:6"/>yet you ſay the Poſſibility of putting it into Execution, will ſtill hinder it and make it A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bortive. That the Landing of any Forreigner would be the Uniting of all our Divided Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties together againſt them; that they would be met with as Vnaminous a Reſolution as when they were thought to have Landed at <hi>Purbeck Iſland</hi> laſt Year. And beſides that, we would Clap up all Papiſts in ſuch a Juncture that they are diſarmed: And even the French themſelves are ſenſible of this; therefore their Fleet and Back is Turned from us toward <hi>Italy and Germany.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though it is not my Deſign to diſpute much about the poſſibility of an Attempt, which I wiſh might be for ever impoſſible; yet for conſcience ſake, and to remove our Countreymens too much ſecurity, I ſay that neither you, nor any man, can know all the Papiſts, French, and other diſaffected, prae-ingaged, Innovators, and Penſioners in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who <hi>Protheus</hi> like, can ſhape themſelves to all Figures: therefore how can you ſecure them all; how can you diſarm them totally: And can you Anſwer for the Sentiments and Intereſt of all the different Parties in <hi>England,</hi> and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in <hi>Ireland,</hi> which ſide they would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline? In <hi>Ireland,</hi> where to one Proteſtant there are three Papiſts, can you vouch they'll ſooner joyn with an Engliſh Heretick than
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101687:7"/>with a French Catholick? So many Ignorant Blind Zealots, ſo many Prieſt-ridden Furies, ſo many outed of their Eſtates on former De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquencies, ſo many Thouſands of Frenchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Officers and Caſhiered Soldiers and Tories ſtraggling there, ſhall they, think you, ſooner joyn with Engliſh, againſt whom they have a blind Antipathy, than with thoſe whom they look upon as damned Miſcreants, Tyrants, Vſurpers of their Countrey and Religion, than with the <hi>French Romaniſts,</hi> whom they would welcome as Saviours and Reſtorers of their All: Nay as they think they loſt all by the Engliſh, they'd venture all they have, <hi>viz.</hi> their Lives, for the French or other Foreigner. Neither can we be aware of all the Arms they may have hid, they may have Conveyed to them ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly; of all the Arms their fury could make uſe of in an uproar? What Store of Arms needed they for the Maſſacre of the <hi>Danes,</hi> or for the Maſſacre of the Proteſtants in <hi>Ireland?</hi> And can't their Holy Father enjoyn again, on ſuch an Occaſion, a <hi>Third Maſſacre</hi> to be prepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated <hi>to the full Honour of the Holy Trinity in Three Perſons?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In a word, what need we ſo much Diſpute Touching the Impoſſibility of an Invaſion, to render our ſelves more ſecure, when our own Hiſtories do convince us how often, to our Coſt,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101687:7"/>ſuch a thing hath been done, which we could not prevent, when for our ſins God would ſuffer it to be, by ſome Art we could not fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee till done. And not to mention our Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Conqueſts, can we forget that ſame in King <hi>John</hi>'s Time, thoſe other Landings of <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Italians</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> in Queen <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> Time, at the Invitation of the Pope and Papiſts? But you'll ſay we were then leſs Powerful, we were then more divided, we have ſtopped thoſe Gapps; and it may be too they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined their Pollicies and Ways of Attacking to the height of your Preparedneſs: and what ever our Power is now, I am ſure the French were never more formidable and more fit to ſtruggle with us. And our ſecret Diviſions are near as great as our open ones were then; a little Spark from abroad, would perhaps, make it break out into a Flame; and our ſecret Enemies are no leſs dangerous than open ones: Theſe can be known and met withal, but thoſe cannot; and would be ready at a Watch-word to follow on the back of us; ariſing, as it were, out of an Ambuſcado.</p>
               <p>Yet all this, dear Countreymen, is ſaid to cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and not to diſhearten us, and to Unite and prepare us; as Fencers do ſhew the ſeveral Paſſes that can be made upon us, for to be ready to parry 'em, if need require.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:101687:8"/>
               <p>My Deſign is not to diſhearten, but to awaken and unite, to ſhew that this is the Greateſt Plot of all, <hi>viz.</hi> to work our Diſunion, which makes all others ſucceſsful.</p>
               <p>For I do not preſume to ſay, That the French are juſt now ready for us, or preparing againſt us, but that the French do preſume to ſet up Claims to our Countrey is apparent to the World in their Books and late Manifeſto's; and give out mean, contemptible Characters of us, to ſeek to raiſe the Spirits of their Natives to triumph over us; that whether ſuch things be done in Joke or Earneſt, it is by ſuch Artifices they began the Conqueſt of our Neighbours; its plain that they never let any of their Pretenſions die, but watch fit opportunities for the execution of them; that the extraordinary number of their preſent Ships, is not anſwerable to any Deſign they might have on any Inland Towns or Places in <hi>Italy</hi> or <hi>Germany.</hi> What uſe is there of Ships to ſail on the Land, that if there were no other Attempt againſt us, their Fleet is ſuch, that it ought to breed Jealouſie and Fears of Encroachments upon the Right of our Soveraignty on theſe Seas, on our Plantations, Sea-port Towns, and our Inward and Outward Trade and Comerce; on the Rights and Priviledges of our Neighbours, who for theſe many Ages ſtood as our Bulwarks and Banks againſt the ſwellings of this ambitious
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101687:8"/>and active Nation, never ſo powerful as now. That his ſtrengthening and manning his Sea-port-Towns ought to be taken notice of, his turning out of all Proteſtant Officers from off his Ships. The Sums of Money he returns to <hi>Rome,</hi> the Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers they make for his Deſigns there, the uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernedneſs that <hi>Rome</hi> and other Popiſh Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours are in touching his vaſt Preparations. The ſtrong Leagues he makes with <hi>Swedeland</hi> and <hi>Denmark,</hi> and with other Princes; wherein he ſtrives to prevent us. All theſe Conſiderations, I ſay, ſhould make us quickly to Re-unite among our ſelves, Prince and People, Diſſenters and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants; and I dare ſay, if a War were thought ſit to be made with <hi>France,</hi> in Vnion with our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, there would be no better means to Re-unite us all; for this is the grand Plot of all other Plots, to keep us ſtill diſunited, to open a gapand inlet in our Body for a Foreigner.</p>
               <p>Yet after all, knowing that the main dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty will ſtill lie herein, to perſwade us that the French are not ſo much our Friends as we believe them to be; and fearing we ſhould be thought to wrong that Nation raſhly or ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, I will more particularly quote ſome of the Authors of the French Politick's Policies, which he propoſes to his King, and will confirm by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Secret and Publick Tranſactions and Matters Fact, that in their continual Practice they do fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101687:9"/>theſe Maximes I will not inſiſt on the means he offers of enſlaving his own Country, let them look to that, of raiſing more the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities power over the People; of deveſting of the Parliaments Prerogatives to inveſt the King therewith; of bringing down the Clergy, that he make the Leeches of the Publick Revenue diſgorge: Let him, I ſay, ſuggeſt means of Arming at Sea, without charge to the Crown, of improving of Trade, and the Colonies and filling of the Kings Coffers: But what hath he to do to be a <hi>Pedagogue</hi> to his Ambitious Prince, for to inſlave other free Nations that have nothing to do with him.</p>
               <p>This Politician then tells his King, That <hi>Spain</hi> is ſlow and ſtupid, and are not ſenſible of any ſmooth trick he may put upon 'em, but only of Affronts upon the Punctilio of Honour, yield 'em in that a little. He incites his Maſter to fill <hi>Portugal</hi> with Soldiers, to act in due time; and that the French Queen her ſelf ought to ſecond this by her Friends in <hi>Spain.</hi> He ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſes him to ſow Diviſions 'twixt the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and the <hi>Hollanders</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> on the other ſide. To bridle <hi>Spain,</hi> and ſet theſe Nations to weaken and undermine each other. Let the King endeavour (ſaith he) to break their Leagues and Allies the one from the other, by feeding them with promiſes of ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101687:9"/>ſupplies on that condition, and of joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the French Fleet to theirs; but they muſt have Orders to Act but for a ſhew and not in earneſt.</p>
               <p>Now he comes to propoſe the ways of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermining <hi>England.</hi> And firſt he calls her Perfidious, and without Faith or Truſt. That <hi>France</hi> ought to make no Treaty or Peace with her, but on advantagious and ambiguous terms; yet he wiſhes his Maſter to diſſemble with <hi>England</hi> for to devour her the laſt. He then begins to declare by what Artificers this King muſt be brought to conceive Jealouſies of his Engliſh Subjects and Parliament, and the Parliament likewiſe of the King; and to bring about that they may not abide the one the other, nor cloſe one with the other.</p>
               <p>In keeping the Engliſh thus in Feudes among themſelves (ſaith he) the French will have time to puſh the Wheel of their Intereſt forward, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote their own Deſigns abroad and againſt us without controul or ſuſpicion, and then it will be eaſie enough to find a pretence to break openly with us, either on the account of the Title of <hi>France</hi> we take, and that the King of <hi>England</hi> muſt be put to it to renounce the ſame; as Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> forced <hi>Francis</hi> the Second of <hi>France</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:101687:10"/>to quit the Title of <hi>England,</hi> they put in the Stile, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or elſe to pick a Quarrel on the Point of the Precedency of our Ambaſſadors.</p>
               <p>Then he comes to ſhew after what manner <hi>France</hi> muſt ſeize on <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſeeing that thence firſt ſprung the Fire (as he ſays) that ſet <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> on a Flame. Then he doubts not but that <hi>Ireland</hi> will carry things very far of it ſelf. Afterwards that Sects muſt be ſet at variance, one Engliſh with another; by which means <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> and the Seventeen <hi>Provinces</hi> were put to Confuſion.</p>
               <p>That the King of <hi>England</hi> muſt be made a Favourer of the Catholicks, and Letters to be framed which muſt be interpreted for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of it. Then that the <hi>Hollander</hi> muſt be flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered that the French will make the Trade fall from <hi>England</hi> into their hands. That <hi>Belle Iſle,</hi> or the Iſland of <hi>Rhe</hi> may be given to the Knights of <hi>Maltha,</hi> who muſt demand of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to reſtore the Commanderies and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices they formerly had here.</p>
               <p>But this Author finding that his Maſter would be too much fettered, by ſeeking out Pretences of Right to Countreys, tells him plainly that he needs ſuch and ſuch places more; and that's reaſon enough (for their Conſcience.) He
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101687:10"/>needs (ſaith he) to get <hi>Strasburg,</hi> the French <hi>Comty,</hi> the State of <hi>Milan,</hi> and of <hi>Gene, Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolongone</hi> and <hi>Piombin;</hi> for to reduce <hi>Suiſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Savoy, Tuſcany, Madera, Parma</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf; that <hi>Sardinia, Naples,</hi> and <hi>Sicily</hi> would follow of themſelves. But that in fine, <hi>Fontaraby, Navarr, Majorca,</hi> and <hi>Minorca,</hi> would ſit him mighty well toward his Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Monarchy Undertaking; but he's a Fool, could not he have put him on the Conquering of <hi>Spain</hi> at his firſt ſtep, and ſo all theſe ſame ſubordinate States would fall to him by courſe.</p>
               <p>Being then in Employ at the French Court, we were told that his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> as ſoon as he read theſe pernicious Maximes, lookt upon one of the <hi>Colberts,</hi> then here Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador, angrily ſaying, <hi>He well perceived that</hi> France <hi>did not coaks him but to deſtroy him.</hi> But that they bragg'd that <hi>Colbert</hi> put it handſomely off, by ſaying, <hi>That this Book was compoſed by</hi> Liſola <hi>the</hi> German, <hi>and to defame</hi> France; which incited the Curious to Examine whether that were true or not, but they found that the ſtile and manner was quite different, and that theſe Maximes were but for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of <hi>France</hi> alone.</p>
               <p>This Manuſcript of the <hi>French Politician,</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:101687:11"/>had lain long in the French Kings Cabinet, whence an Officer was found to have ſtollen a Copy of it; then it was printed clandeſtinely, and care was taken for the ſuppreſſing it.</p>
               <p>But to evince it more cloſely and undeniably, that that Book, with the other, which I quoted above, came out of the French Mint, that's out of their Cabinets; I'll manifeſt it by their late Practice in every one of thoſe Maximes, that are ſet down in the <hi>French Politician.</hi> It's true, that Mareſchal <hi>Villeroy,</hi> a great Stateſman, was wont to reduce the main Stratagems, by which they wheadled their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, to theſe two, <hi>Par Finance &amp; Fineſſe,</hi> that is by Money and Cunning and Conney too, which is one of their chief Nets to catch their Neighbours in. But to come to particulars, Their chief Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices for dividing and undermining their Friends, may be reduced to theſe following: 1. By <hi>Sinons</hi> or pretended Fugitives. 2. By Pentioners in our Councils. 3. By Alliances and French La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. 4. By breaking open and diciphering our Secreteſs Letters. 5. By ſending Auxiliaries that favour our Enemies. 6. By Ambiguous Treaties, to gain time and advantage of breaking them. 7. By ſpreading Slaunders and fomenting Jea: louſies betwixt the Kings and their People. 8. By entertaining a ſecret League with the Turk.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:101687:11"/>
               <p>Now to begin with thoſe more general and remote means, which <hi>France</hi> takes to divide her Neighbours in their Leagues and Amity. She uſually calls in the Turk upon the back of 'em; and this <hi>moſt Chriſtian</hi> King will not ſtick to enter into ſecret Covenants with that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian Tyrant againſt the reſt of Chriſtendom. I need not mount up ſo high as <hi>Francis</hi> the I. <hi>Henry</hi> the II. and other their Succeſſors, who openly brought in the Turk againſt <hi>Charles</hi> the V. and other Emperors; publick Hiſtories can bear me Witneſs in it. <hi>Rincon</hi> and <hi>Fregoſe</hi> were taken by the way, ſeized with Inſtructions from <hi>Francis</hi> the I<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to <hi>Soliman,</hi> to excite this Infidel to War againſt the Chriſtian Princes; and when any of <hi>Francis</hi> his Neighbours would upbraid him with ſuch Antichriſtian Treacheries, he could put it off but with a Drollery: <hi>What,</hi> ſays he, <hi>May not I, when beſet with Wolves, call in for Dogs to help me.</hi> But to come to our times, What made the French to be the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the loſs of <hi>Candia,</hi> and to yield the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage at <hi>Gigerys</hi> and <hi>Hongary,</hi> but for to manage the Turkiſh Amity to oppoſe him to the Emperor, if he proffers to ſtir or to enter into Tripple League. They ſent ſome Supplies, 'tis true, to dazzle the World, but when <hi>La Feuil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lade</hi> (who knew not the Secret) brought his Men to an Engagement, he was oppoſed by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101687:12"/>
                  <hi>Coligny;</hi> who had Orders to do things but for a ſhew. Beſides, the King ſent Counter Orders with ſome of the major Officers, which they were to read, but when they came to <hi>Candia;</hi> Monſieur <hi>De Louvas</hi> hindred many of the moſt valiant and conſiderable Officers, Gentry and Soldiers, to go thither, even as Voluntiers. In fine, The Diviſions, Counter-ſeaſons, and wilful Miſunderſtandings of the French with their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, in that occaſion, did more to the loſs of the City, than the Batteries of the Turks, who had ſpent ſome ſcore years in vain toward the Conqueſt of that place, but could never get it out of the <hi>Venetians</hi> ſingle hands, till theſe double-dealing French Friends came into help more toward the loſing of it than the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining it; ſo that the <hi>Venetians</hi> might have had more reaſon to ſend back theſe French Supplies than they had in returning home Prince <hi>Alme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> of <hi>Modena's</hi> Succours upon ſome ſuch ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicion.</p>
               <p>And the Turkiſh Embaſſador (a thing very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſual to be ſent from the Ottoman Grandeur) who afterwards was diſpatch'd to the French Court, unriddles the Matter, and though the King made the difficile and ſcornful with him, yet he ſent Orders to careſs him and make much of him in ſecret; as looking upon the Mahumetans to be one of the chief Supporters of his Crown and State.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:101687:12"/>
               <p>And as the French will be Friends with the Turks to uſe 'em againſt their Enemies, ſo with thoſe they pretend openly to help, as their Friends, they deal as with Turks in effect, by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derhand Conſpiracies; I mean in their Auxiliary Supplies to their Allies: Their Succours tend but to leave 'em in the lurch, to be deſroyed by their Concurrents; that when he hath ingaged the Frog and ſilly Mouſe to a Fight, to weaken the one the other, he, the French Kite, might the more eaſily ſnatch 'em both away in his greedy Talons. Beſides what we alledged above of his treacherous Auxiliaries to <hi>Hongary</hi> and <hi>Candia,</hi> we may intimate thoſe he ſent ſome years ago to help <hi>Holland</hi> againſt the Biſhop of <hi>Munſter;</hi> and a little afterwards on the ſame Claims ſets <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> again <hi>Holland;</hi> and when it came to the puſh, leaves him to the mercy of the <hi>Hollander,</hi> all he ſought for, being but to ſeek to deſtroy theſe two (Supporters of <hi>Flanders</hi>) the one by the Hands of the other. His Deſign was the ſame touching <hi>England,</hi> when of late he ſent his Fleet to aſſiſt us againſt <hi>Holland,</hi> with ſecret Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to <hi>d'Eſtree,</hi> to leave the Engliſh and Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lander to deſtroy each other.</p>
               <p>While <hi>France,</hi> both at the Treaty of the Pire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nees, and afterwards, had ſworn a firm Offenſive and Dofenſive League with <hi>Spain;</hi> they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand ſought to weaken their Allies, by ſending men and money with <hi>Colbert, Schomberg,</hi> and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101687:13"/>under <hi>Turenne</hi>'s Name, as Voluntiers to the Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuguezes, till a Ship that was taken by the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, happily diſcovered that the Portuguezes were ſtirred up and incouraged by the French in their Attempts againſt the Catholick King. <hi>France,</hi> by reaſon of a French Princeſs, ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be the greateſt Friend in the World to <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but to ſhew what Friendſhip that was, they manage with <hi>Swedeland</hi> that Treaty of <hi>Stumdorff</hi> ſeemingly in favour to the Polanders, but in effect very prejudicial to them, and in the mean time <hi>Avagour, Lombres,</hi> and <hi>Bezi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eres,</hi> are imployed to ſet theſe Crowns toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Ears, and to perſwade King <hi>Cazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> of <hi>Poland</hi> to lay down his Crown, to make way for <hi>Conde, Newburg,</hi> or for ſome other Vota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>France.</hi> Moreover, while this coakſing Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did hugg the Emperour, he finds ſuch Papers in the taking of <hi>Muran,</hi> a Fortreſs in the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper Hungaria,</hi> which manifeſtly ſhewed that the French had in the mean time incouraged the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garians in this Rebellion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Another Artifice of theirs is to ſend out <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons,</hi> or protended Eugitives, which are forſooth baniſhed from their Court, yet theſe are in a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Intelligence with them to ſend to 'em all Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Intelligences, by ſeeming to betray <hi>France</hi> to that Nation whereunto they ſly. Thus have we known and ſeen Monſieur <hi>Gourville</hi> to be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht, as it were upon the account of <hi>Foucquet</hi> to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101687:13"/>
                  <hi>Bruſſells, Madrid,</hi> and the <hi>Hague.</hi> There to ſcrew himſelf into favour, he communicated to 'em ſome empty Secrets, to hide from them the true State of Affairs of <hi>France.</hi> His Couriers did ſeemingly go from <hi>Paris</hi> to <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and backward again; and in this Hurry, Courſe and Intercourſe, he fed the Spaniards but with Chymera's, and ſent an Accompt of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Deſigns into <hi>France:</hi> But after all, when this Impoſtor was found out by the Spaniard, he was as heartily wellcommed at <hi>Paris,</hi> as if no grudge had ever been; and from Intendant of the Prince of <hi>Conde</hi>'s, he was received into an inner favour. I could mention the <hi>Guizes</hi> in former times, who were baniſht, to gull the Proteſtants, and ſome of late ſent into <hi>England,</hi> and perhaps the Earl of <hi>S.</hi> (who in their Language makes ſixteen) is this laſt month fled hither into <hi>England,</hi> upon no other occaſion.</p>
               <p n="4">4. What ſhould I run over the particulars I above promiſed to demonſtrate, when all obſerving perſons may prove them to themſelves. When his late breaches of the Treaties of the Pyrenees, of <hi>Breda,</hi> of <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> and of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> do ſhew that <hi>France</hi> values no otherwiſe ſuch Ties, than <hi>Liſander</hi> did the ſolemneſt Oaths, that is to deceive men thereby, and to get a fit opportunity of breaking them to his advantage. But we intend to ſet forth ſhortly an Abſtract of the Treaties of <hi>France</hi> with the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> in this laſt Century, and the Reaſons of the Alternative Growth and Decline of each of theſe, and therein it will from the words of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Impartial Hiſtorians appear, how far the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101687:14"/>French are to be truſted to in this point of Tranſactions and Covenants.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Now as to the uſe they may make of Emiſſaries and Penſioners abroad, to make Factions in the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Courts; the clear-ſighted know that Monſieur <hi>Vaubrun</hi> was ſent into <hi>Germany</hi> but for to ſtir <hi>Serin</hi> and <hi>Ragotzi,</hi> againſt the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> Each one may perceive that the Prince <hi>Furſtemburg,</hi> who is in <hi>Bavaria,</hi> does act in conſort with the other <hi>Furſtemberg,</hi> that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides in <hi>France:</hi> And that Monſieur <hi>Gremonville</hi> was the occaſion of the Revolt in <hi>Hungary;</hi> for which and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Diviſions he wrought in <hi>Vienna,</hi> he was expell'd more civilly than he deſerved.</p>
               <p>The Archbiſhop of <hi>Gneſne</hi> and the Mareſchal <hi>Sobieski,</hi> were the Penſioners that <hi>France</hi> bragg'd of in the Court of <hi>Poland;</hi> and of ſome alſo in ours, which could be named, but that a reſpectful tenderneſs for my Countrymen makes me more reſerved, and ſhall ſhut them up in my own Breaſt, hoping they have ſince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of ſuch baſe and unnatural Treacheries, toward their generous and gracious King, and dear Countrey; eſpecially knowing ſome of 'em to be dead, and others almoſt dying: which were mentioned in Parliament.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Now touching French Princeſſes they match out, to have occaſion thereby to divide their Neighbours, God forbid that I ſhould think that all the Ladies of that Rank were <hi>Fredegonde, Brunehaut,</hi> or <hi>Helena</hi> like, but that as this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was the occaſion of the ſubtle <hi>Grecians</hi> getting foot into the Trojan Territories, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101687:14"/>of imbroyling and ravaging it by long Wars; ſo I obſerved that moſt commonly thoſe French Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes are Engines of State, to carry along with 'em abroad Correſponding Colonies of that reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, ambitious, and intriguing Nation, to make the intereſt of that Court where they go to bend to that of their Native Countrey, which they ever love beſt. I'll but glance at Examples, The very memory of <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Nevers</hi> is odious in <hi>Poland,</hi> by whoſe occaſion that Country was brought into ſuch inward Diſturbances and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, that not long ago King <hi>Cazimir</hi> himſelf at laſt was fain to quit the Crown for a quiet Coole in the Abbey of St. <hi>Germain</hi> at <hi>Paris</hi> But the obſervant in Publick Affairs may find freſh Preſidents hereof in <hi>Tuſcany, Portugal,</hi> and perhaps <hi>England</hi> not long ſince; and I am affraid that Lady they of late ſent to <hi>Spain,</hi> will be the pretence in time to come, of making more Demands than that of <hi>Maſtrick,</hi> which they would now go about.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Hitherto we have toucht of the Cauſes or Inſtruments the French do make uſe of, now of the Effect, which is Diviſions in Foreign Courts, either to cut out work for ſuch at home, that they may be no Obſtacle to the Carier of the French Conqueſts; or to make a Breach among us, at which they may creep in more eaſily. For the proof hereof, for brevities ſake I'll refer you to what I hinted above, touching the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101687:15"/>the French Emiſſaries wrought in <hi>Poland</hi> in and before the year 71, and likewiſe about and before that time in <hi>Germany,</hi> when their Agents ſwarmed there to ſow thoſe Seeds of War which we have ſince ſeen ſprung up to ſuch a height as cannot be yet cut down nor extirpated poſſibly by all the hands in <hi>Europe. Colbert</hi> the Junior (as I mention'd before) not long ſince carried away Corn and Coin, <hi>viz.</hi> Thirty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Crowns into <hi>Portugal,</hi> by way of Loan as it were, to raiſe the Countrey againſt the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard, and ſo make a Diverſion from <hi>Flanders.</hi> But the Inſtructions and Covenants whereby the French required ſome Sea-port Towns on the Coaſt of <hi>Spain</hi> to be given to themſelves (as I warrant you they'll ſerve no Friend for nothing) theſe I ſay were ſeized in another Ship that ſtraggled into the Spaniards Nett, where all the Mine was diſcovered. Such was the Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances they wrought in <hi>Lorrain,</hi> that the late Duke (ſomewhat guilty thereof himſelf) dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully cried out, <hi>That the Neighbour hood of</hi> France <hi>was a ſmoke that would drive him out of his own Countrey and Eſtate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What ſhould I mention the Jealouſies, Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Diviſions, which we with tears behold here to be wrought by them in our <hi>England</hi> and its Dependants, when any unbyaſs'd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering perſon may perceive that they ſtrive to repeat the Scenes of the late Inteſtine Tragedy,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101687:15"/>wherein that Wicked French Embaſſadour Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Thou,</hi> by his Agents confeſſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented too late, to have acted here the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, by traducing, blaſting, and heightning in that moderate Royal Martyr a propenſity to Popery, forſooth, by miſ-repreſenting the King to the People, the People and Parliament to the King, by unſuſpected Inſtruments; by contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving means to divide the unwary Proteſtants about Formalities and petit Differences, about Indifferent Things, wherein it is impoſſible to unite 'em in, no otherwiſe than by Charity, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Patience; for Perſecution is obſerved to increaſe Proſelites, and make 'em more zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and vertuous; which otherwiſe without op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition would languiſh and decay: but if the work be of God, as <hi>Gamaliel</hi> ſaid, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be deſtroyed by Men by all art or power. When by ſuch Artifices the French and Jeſuit had blinded ſome Diſſenting Zealots with ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pretences of removing evil Councellors and of ſome Incroachments, then things being ripe, the greedy Lawleſs Souldier is brought on the Stage, to make our King and People bleed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without ſeeing the Hook, but too late; when at firſt moderate and impartial Counſels might have healed things, if they might be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to come to an underſtanding, and to touch the Root of the Diſeaſe; <hi>Sed quid haec ingrata revolvo.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:101687:16"/>
               <p>But remember in a word, That whether Times tend to a further Diſ-union of Spirits, or to a thorow Union, yet in either Juncture the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God and Man will ſoon find out thoſe baſe <hi>Sinons,</hi> thoſe Incendiaries, thoſe French Penſioners and Lawleſs Stateſmen, that ſeek to divide the good Father and his poor Children, and to rent miſerably their own Mothers Bowels for private ends by unworthy Policies. And thoſe Perſons or Party (whatever it be) which recede moſt from French Devices and Popiſh Forms, and ſhall in their plain meaning and counſels, tend but to cloſe to the honeſt Fundamental Laws of their Countrey and of the Goſpel, after a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, loyal, and charitable Interpretation; they and only they ſhall prevail and be in requeſt with their King and Countrey at the long Run; for that God will be above Man. In fine, I refer to the Reader to judge, and to our Superiors to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, Whether the mean propoſed in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſcourſe (which lay by me) be ſo ſeaſonable or practicable, which however I meant to be of this uſe, to make a Diverſion of all Engliſhmens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bitterneſs and choller, againſt a more fit Object and Enemy; that they may ceaſe to look upon one another with a ſharp Eye, but look off rather towards abroad, whence the Spring of our Diviſions come; <hi>viz.</hi> from <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101687:16"/>
               <head>THE <hi>French Politician <hi>FOUND OUT.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the greateſt dangers of <hi>Spain</hi> were from <hi>England,</hi> by reaſon of our power at Sea, and that we could block up the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ports at pleaſure; this <hi>our Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur</hi> believed as firmly, as if it had been an Article of his Creed, and that the Plot, as he had laid it, in its ſucceſs was Infallible.</p>
               <p>'Tis a Truth. But if it were ſome years ago the Intereſt of this Crown to accord to that Maxim; Time, and the preſent weakneſſes of <hi>Spain (ſinking
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101687:17"/>under its own burdens)</hi> have turn'd the Ballance, and made it impracticable. The Face and State of Affairs are now very much changed. <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Seventh</hi> was too nearly allied with the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the <hi>Catholic,</hi> not to have <hi>oppos'd the Cabals,</hi> which were then formed againſt <hi>Mary,</hi> to bereave her of the <hi>Low-Countries.</hi> His Son <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eighth</hi> followed the ſame Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels; and if at any times <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Fifth</hi> was travers'd by him, it aroſe from that juſt Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion he had of his growing Grandeurs; Fortune being more favourable to him, than to <hi>Francis</hi> the <hi>Firſt,</hi> whoſe loſs had been a fair Step unto his own.</p>
               <p>Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> harboured the ſame Jealouſies; for <hi>Spain,</hi> puffed up with a long continued courſe of proſperous ſucceſſes, was not arriv'd to that pitch of Declenſion we ſee it now adays. And if <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Firſt</hi> beheld with an Eye of Envy the progreſs of <hi>France, Charles</hi> the <hi>Second</hi> might do it alſo, his Fear being much more warrantable, becauſe that Kingdom is grown more powerful, more formidable than when his Father reigned. And there be Arguments of Glory, Revenge, and Intereſt for my Aſſertion, all which, according to the beſt of my judgment, are ſtrictly interwoven one within the other.</p>
               <p>Glory demands the continuance of the <hi>(triple)</hi> League; becauſe this had twice bridled a Prince who had ſlip'd out of it, and who, without this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101687:17"/>Reſtraint, would have over-run all bounds by reaſon of his unmeaſurable Ambition, the ſole and unvariable Rule of all his Undertakings. Beſides, it can be no diſhonour unto <hi>England</hi> to be reproach'd of <hi>France,</hi> as heretofore, of ſlackneſs in aſſiſting her, and that we loved to prolong and foment her Civil Wars, if not to make them perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual.</p>
               <p>Revenge is yet another and ſtronger Motive to invigorate us in our conduct, whether you reflect upon what is paſt, or on things preſent. For the preſent, 'tis well known that the <hi>French</hi> promiſes are only tendred us for the better inabling them to play their own Game; and the miſchiefs they are now a brewing, ſhould now inſpire us with a greater abhorrency of their greater maſqued Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies.</p>
               <p>Moreover, thoſe brave Methods propounded by our <hi>French Politician</hi> for the ſubverſion of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, whoſe Glory Eclipſeth theirs, are no longer with any patience to be endured.</p>
               <p>Add farther that injurious manner wherewith they treat <hi>England,</hi> becauſe it carries the Ballance of <hi>Europe,</hi> and ſupports the Oppreſſed againſt their Violence and Tyranny.</p>
               <p>And could we not remember thoſe Invectives wherewith they have wounded the whole Nation, yet this ſhould be conſidered, that they never ſpared the Sacred perſons of our Princes.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:101687:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ribier</hi> is pleas'd to ſtrew theſe ſweet Flowers upon <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eighth,</hi> viz. <hi>That he was the moſt Inſidel and unconſtant Prince of his Age, full of Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and Double dealing, whoſe Soul Symboliz'd with the Seas environing his Iſland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the fore-mentioned Author of the <hi>French Politicks</hi> adviſeth, that the King now reigning ſhould be voic'd a <hi>Roman Catholic,</hi> thereby to procure him his Subjects hatred, and to Augment it be feigned Letters written to ſome of the leading <hi>Proteſtant Lords,</hi> to render them ſuſpected, and procure their Ruin by a Maxim, which with extream imprudence they themſelves have divulged to the World.</p>
               <p>Theſe Counſels and Invectives were all forged by them, becauſe <hi>Henry</hi> would not turn the Scales wholly of their ſide to deſtroy <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>England</hi> in conſequence thereof, which without this invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible Obſtruction, muſt have been together by the ſame Torrent overwhelmed.</p>
               <p>And as to what concerns <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> that general intereſt, in which inſenſibly he is engaged, affords Alliment to a damn'd Plot, which is by them ſecretly carried on againſt him. But I paſs this by, and come to the Queſtion under debate.</p>
               <p>And it is this: That the Conſideration of what is paſt ſhould ſo far influence a potent Prince, who hath his Sword in his hands, as to carve out his own ſatisfactions from them, whoſe inſenſibleneſs of doing wrongs raiſeth them to ſuch a degree of Inſolence, as to deride us.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:101687:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aquitain, Normandy,</hi> and their dependant Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces, together with <hi>Guyſnes, Ardres, Bouloign,</hi> and <hi>Calais,</hi> ancient Demeans of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> are ſuch important pieces, and their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt ſo eaſie, that they will ſurrender themſelves as ſoon as <hi>England</hi> ſhall ſeriouſly invade them; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, that the Obligation of the League and Powers compoſing it, remain firm and inviolable; and that from a meer defenſive War we become Aggreſſors, and deſpoil him of thoſe Trophies, who, after the glorious Example of his Anceſtors, hath enlarg'd the bounds of his own Dominions on the wrack and loſſes of his Neighbours.</p>
               <p>But and if this Deſign be delay'd, and leaſure given <hi>France</hi> to debaſe <hi>Spain,</hi> then all muſt yield to the rapid courſe of that Nation, who is now making Chains for us, nay, carrieth them with her, to bind and enſlave ſuch who ſhall firſt make head againſt her, and at long run, of all thoſe who either ſecretly or openly maintained or abetted this horrible Deſign againſt the common and public ſafety. And let her Neighbours be once brought down, <hi>England</hi> deveſted of her Friends will be little more than the work of one day, and muſt fall in that very moment ſhe is Aſſaulted. The pretext is ready, either <hi>England</hi> ſhall loſe the Title of <hi>France,</hi> or <hi>France</hi> will uſurp that of <hi>England.</hi> I'le explain my ſelf ſomewhat more largely.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:101687:19"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>France</hi> being now rid, and ſtanding in no longer fear of her Competitors, will infallibly break with <hi>England,</hi> imitating herein Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who quarrell'd with <hi>Francis</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> for Entituling himſelf Heir of that Crown ſhe poſſeſſed, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhe was exceeding jealous, <hi>Mary</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> having furniſhed her Husband with a Title. But ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe this colourable pretence be neglected, yet will he ſerve himſelf of one more remote; for who ſo hath a mind to pick quarrels, and wage War, will never talk ſo big and loud, as the whole World may hear him. I'le not lead you far to fetch an Inſtance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lewis,</hi> Son of <hi>Philip Auguſtus,</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> reigned in <hi>England,</hi> maugre all the oppoſitions of King <hi>John,</hi> who was depoſed for his Tyrannies. At length <hi>John</hi> having recollected his miſcarriages, reconciled himſelf with the Pope, becomes his Tributary, demulceth his Holineſs with his golden Promiſes, and profound Submiſſions, and <hi>Lewis</hi> unfortunately loſeth his newly acquir'd Crown. 'Tis true, he bequeathed the Right thereof (ſuch an one as it is) unto his Succeſſors; who preſerve it carefully, and aſſert it publicly, in a formal Prayer ſung in theſe expreſs words at their Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>viz. That he will never relinquiſh the Scepter of the ancient</hi> Saxons, Mercians, <hi>and other Princes, who have reign'd in</hi> England. And therefore the Kings of <hi>France,</hi> ſince <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>Eighth,</hi> may with more juſtice, ſay they, aſſume the Title of Kings of <hi>England,</hi> than the Kings of <hi>England</hi> ſtyle themſelves Kings of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:101687:19"/>
               <p>It was <hi>Ribbir</hi> that ſet up this imaginary Title, and ſuggeſted unto <hi>France</hi> a pretext and ground for falling out with <hi>England</hi> upon the firſt and next favourable opportunity. I have given her the firſt Intelligence of the Thunderbolt: <hi>England</hi> may yet in time avoid it.</p>
               <p>Is it to be imagin'd that <hi>Lovois,</hi> and many great ones, whoſe Fortune and that of their Friends depends upon Warlike Employments, will not now ſtir their King to thoſe new attempts againſt <hi>England,</hi> (in caſe they want other Employment) ſhewing unto him the eaſineſs of it, from the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Jealouſies, and Unprovidedneſs that <hi>England</hi> is in, and the many ſecret Friends they have here. But in caſe they did alter theſe Meaſures, or not now execute them, yet ſeeing our forwardneſs; and our Spirits, Eyes, and Arms, to be up and ready for them; that, I ſay, will make ſtill our condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions better with them, whether we ſtand their Enemies, Friends, or Neuters; otherwiſe they will be more apt to ſlight both the one and the other.</p>
               <p>But laſtly, let's give Intereſt leave to follow Revenge, and ſhew what Meaſures we ought to take from the Conſideration of this cogent Topic. I confeſs the Motive is interwoven with that of Glory; but yet more firmly, becauſe it runs on two Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and both of vaſt weight and conſequence; the one is particular and private Intereſt, the other is more general and public. This laſt aims at the common Repoſe of <hi>Europe,</hi> and its care and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101687:20"/>endeavour muſt be to reſtrain the Ambition of thoſe two great Potentates, who court the Empire, which cannot be effected without conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>England</hi>'s Peace at home, and confining thoſe two inraged Neighbours to their juſt and reſpective Bounds, that if one of them ſhould win any thing from his Rival, he may not preſently invade <hi>England,</hi> who became an idle Spectator of their Actions, without cheriſhing their mutual Enmities, and giving a Curb to their ſeveral Enterprizes. If Reaſon of State ſpeaks loudly in deaf Ears, Glory doth it in ſhriller and clearer Terms.</p>
               <p>But over and above this general Peace of <hi>Europe,</hi> wherein I could wiſh <hi>England</hi> were occupied, there is ſomewhat in ſpecial that ſhould rouſe her up from her preſent Lethargic drowſineſs, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>France</hi> brags how facil it is to blind her Eyes, and cauſe her to take what new Meaſures ſhe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth.</p>
               <p>You will ſay theſe are points of grand Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Convince <hi>England</hi> of them. Well! I ſhall debate of both immediately.</p>
               <p>Let's firſt touch at this of the common Safety, and we will in the next place conſider of the proper means to bound <hi>France,</hi> that ſhe may not abuſe their Credulity, who can certainly and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely mortifie her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marillac,</hi> Ambaſſadour for <hi>Francis</hi> the <hi>Firſt,</hi> thus writes to his Maſter from <hi>London,</hi> that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were diſpleaſed they had ſuffered the <hi>French</hi> to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101687:20"/>
                  <hi>Ardres,</hi> and that before it was too late, they would hinder the finiſhing thoſe Fortifications: Adding, <q>
                     <hi>That they were vext to the Heart that the King had fortified</hi> Ardres, <hi>and that they repented very much to have permitted our men proceed ſo far, that yet notwithſtanding they had time enough to reduce matters to their former ſtate, becauſe they had been informed that</hi> Ardres <hi>could not yet in one whole year be ſo repaired, but that it might be as eaſily forc'd.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But if <hi>Ardres,</hi> which is no more than a ſhadow of what <hi>France</hi> poſſeſſeth in the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> did heretofore ſtrike a Jealouſie into <hi>England,</hi> ſhould not that groſs multitude of important Towns, and the Thirds of a large and vaſt Eſtate, render her now by far much more jealous? eſpecially ſince it hath given ſuch fearful and violent ſhocks unto the whole Land, made another Neighbour Republick tremble, yea and it trembles to this very day at their near Approaches; the <hi>French</hi> Armies being led on by a mighty Captain trained up in the School of buſineſs, enur'd to Hardſhips and fortunate Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes in all his Conduct and Adminiſtrations. And <hi>Ardres</hi> (to ſay nothing of <hi>Calais</hi> and <hi>Graveling</hi>) is ſomething leſs than <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> if it be conſidered according to the preſent Eſtimate that <hi>France</hi> doth ſet upon it. Theſe two places are the two Ports, from whence one day the Storm ſhall be wafted over into <hi>England,</hi> if <hi>England</hi> ſuffer <hi>France</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporate the Naval Forces of <hi>Holland</hi> with her
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101687:21"/>own, and to inoculate that fair Bud into her Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Crown. Perſons of the weakeſt Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may without difficulty penetrate into the Iſſues and Succeſſes of ſuch an Union.</p>
               <p>And let it be remembred, that <hi>France</hi> was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly invenem'd againſt <hi>England</hi> for redemanding <hi>Calais,</hi> and having once got it out of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> hands, ſhe wanted neither Armies, nor any other conſiderable means, to make a ſure and ſpeedy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of other places.</p>
               <p>If Fear then bounded their proceedings, becauſe it was not ſo eaſie a matter to diſpoſſeſs the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> where once they had got footing; yet was it eaſie enough to diſſeiſe and unrooſt others, either by Force or Treaty, as they did juſtly enough by that of <hi>Vervins;</hi> yet now the Tables are turn'd, for they once underſtanding that <hi>Spain</hi> is brought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her knees, the Conqueſt of that and <hi>England</hi> will not coſt much time nor pains. The Balance being now removed, their Forces augment daily, and like a violent Inundation carry all before them. It's true, this is yet impoſſible if <hi>England</hi> do not ſtand neuter, while other Nations are entering in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to more than a Triple League; which to effect the one and hinder the other, they turn every ſtone, they embarraſs all Affairs, they ſupport the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue with a thouſand hopes, and thoſe hopes with a profuſe expence of Treaſure, which forceth a paſſage through thoſe ſordid Souls, whoſe ſole Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt is their private Gain and Advantage. And that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101687:21"/>which is moſt ſurprizing is this, they engage the Favourites, who are Lords of th' Aſcendant at Court or elſewhere, and at this rate believe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves potent enough to give what Laws they pleaſe to all politick Tranſactions, if ſo be the true In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt give ground unto the falſe, which is cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, changeable, and infallibly deſtructive to them that do embrace it.</p>
               <p>And by theſe means they of late out the <hi>Gordian</hi> Knot of that Triple League, as if they were cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure beforehand of their deſigns, and their buſineſs were already done unto their hands; <hi>Pomponne</hi> was diſpatch'd into <hi>Swedeland,</hi> to diſengage that Crown from the League by the golden promiſes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, Penſions, and Preſents, which will go very far in a poor Countrey, and remove whatever Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacle ſtands in his way to the Empire of all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The worſt is, that in <hi>France</hi> at thoſe times they did publiſh this Negotiation, branding <hi>England</hi> with the goodly Names of <hi>Unconſtant and Perſidious.</hi> Which brings to my mind a ſtory of the <hi>Viſcount of Narbonne,</hi> who told an <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>That ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Tun of Wine and a Penſion had quickly ſent them back again to England.</hi>
                  </q> The other anſwering, <q>
                     <hi>It was a Tribute and no Penſion.</hi>
                  </q> This was in the Reign of <hi>Lewis</hi> XI. who diſengaged <hi>England</hi> from ſuccouring the Dukes of <hi>Burgundy and Bretaigne.</hi> The Jeſt was biting, but 'tis the uſual Coyn where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with <hi>France</hi> pays ſuch whom it openly flatters, that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101687:22"/>ſo ſhe may if poſſible ruin and ſtrangle them the more cunningly.</p>
               <p>A League with <hi>England</hi> blocks up the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Havens, ſo ſaith <hi>du Pleſſis;</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> are hot and intent upon it. Truth is, the Daughter of Time and Time muſt diſcover the events of this Maxim. Onely let me add by the way, that if <hi>France</hi> cannot prevail with <hi>England</hi> to do this Jobb for her, ſhe will tack about and treat with <hi>Spain</hi> upon other terms, that relinquiſhing the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Netherlands ſhe ſhall be recompenced more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly with the Spoils of ſome other parts of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> which <hi>France</hi> will conquer for her. We will unriddle this Myſtery, and let <hi>England</hi> ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caſtillon</hi> in his Embaſſie for <hi>Francis</hi> I. writing from <hi>London</hi> adviſeth his Maſter to a League with <hi>Spain</hi> againſt <hi>England;</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>For (ſaith he) I would ever counſel Your Majesty to quit other deſigns, and accord with Spain, and to give this Kingdom in prey, which may be with more facility and leſs expence effected, than to take Calais; for the expence cannot laſt above one moneth or ſix weeks at the moſt. Divide England between you, and let each take thoſe parts of it which lie moſt commodious and convenient for him.</hi>
                  </q> And in the cloſe he ſubjoyns, <q>
                     <hi>Your Majeſty may keep Wales, and Cornwall, and Scotland for your ſelf, and leave the ſorry remainders unto the Emperour.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>There be three things worthy our obſervation from this Embaſſadors Advice. The one is, that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101687:22"/>
                  <hi>France</hi> believed ſhe might cheat <hi>Spain</hi> into this treacherous Conqueſt, provided <hi>Spain</hi> would but ſacrifice to her Covetouſneſs and Ambition the <hi>Low Countries.</hi> The ſecond is, that <hi>Spain</hi> keeps faſt and faithful to the Publick, and prefers it before her own private Intereſt. And then laſtly, becauſe of this Phantaſtick League <hi>England</hi> muſt immediately and infallibly be conquer'd as ſoon as invaded, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially let her be once abandon'd of her Allies, and that <hi>France</hi> have brought <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> upon their knees, and hath united their ſcattered disjoynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Naval Forces with her own. I truſt my Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are plain, ſo plain that the meaneſt Capacity can comprehend me.</p>
               <p>Alliances betwixt Crowns bring little profit to the People. This is viſible in the Matches between the two Royal Houſes of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England;</hi> for no ſooner was <hi>Henrietta Maria</hi> wedded unto King <hi>Charles,</hi> but State-Intereſt and the Capricious Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours of the Favourites interrupted that Peace, which a long time before had continued between both Kingdoms, and by the Marriage was ſworn to be perpetuated. Experience alſo of what had paſt might have render'd <hi>Spain</hi> more adviſed, and to have avoided that ſnare, into which ſhe ran through falſe Maxims, with a great deal of Joy.</p>
               <p>I'le onely quote one paſſage out of the Memoirs of the Duke of <hi>Sully;</hi> he then writing to <hi>Henry</hi> IV. about his Intrigues with <hi>Spain</hi> tells him; <q>
                     <hi>That the growth of one Prince is the diminution of another;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101687:23"/>that no Parentage, Affinities, Leagues, Peace, Treaties, Agreements, Oaths, or reciprocal Promiſes, could ever yield ſufficient Precautions for time to come againſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of State.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>I could wiſh this Memoir affixed on the Cabinet of <hi>Madrid</hi> for their future Reformation, and that in time to come they would take other Meaſures; ſith <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. adheres moſt pertinaciouſly to the Maxims of <hi>Sully,</hi> and that after a Treaty ſworn with the greateſt ſeriouſneſs and ſolemnity, and a Ceſſion of all Rights made and verified in due form of Law. For inſtead of obſerving it they are now debating other Rights, and demand an hundred things, which being refuſed, they take up Arms, and proceed to the worſt Acts of Hoſtility, leaving us without hopes of any Calm to follow upon this Storm, which menaceth with an univerſal Deluge all the <hi>Netherlands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Give me leave to ſubjoyn one important Advice unto <hi>England:</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>The Right of</hi> Edward III. (ſaith <hi>Laboureur) is not worth the mentioning, were it not to tell the world how unrighteous the Engliſh are in their pretentions to it, and to manifeſt what neceſſity lieth on us to keep that Nation at a bay, at a diſtance from us, which is naturally quarrelſom, born our Enemy, and that will borrow Aſſistance whereever ſhe can get it, and take up any the leaſt pretext in the world to ſubdue and ruine us. Robert Abbot of La Celle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd an Engliſh Prelate with this, that his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen in their Inclinations reſembled that Element
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101687:23"/>which did encompaſs them, that is to ſay, they were cruel, proud, unconſtant, and ſeditious.</hi>
                  </q> Theſe are noble Elogies indeed conſerr'd upon your Friends, <hi>Monſieur,</hi> in a time of perfect peace, nay upon your beſt and moſt potent Friends, to whom you have in this preſent Juncture of Affairs your Recourſe, and who are guilty of this very great Overſight, to ſuffer themſelves to be charmed by your Flatteries and Cozenages.</p>
               <p>When as Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> redemanded <hi>Calais</hi> for juſt Reaſons ſhe then alleaged, the <hi>French</hi> reſolved rather to endure a War, wherewith ſhe menac'd them, than to ſurrender it: <q>
                     <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſaith the ſame <hi>Laboureur) there was a double danger, one to ſuffer our ancient Enemies to get footing in the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent of France; and then too becauſe they are Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, who would always have a Faction in the State to revive their old Quarrels at pleaſure; and that it more concern'd us now than heretofore, to ſhut them up with their new Religion on the other ſide the Sea.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>This was done in the Sale of <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> and if any other place offer it ſelf to purchaſe, <hi>France</hi> will be no Higler, but purchaſe it at any rate, ſuppoſing ſhe be diſcharged of her Wars with <hi>Spain.</hi> Again, Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> inſiſting ſtill upon the Reſtitution of <hi>Calais,</hi> and ſpeaking of it unto <hi>Sancy,</hi> he after ſeveral ſhifts and excuſes, <q>
                     <hi>By God, Madam,</hi> (quoth he) <hi>can Your Majeſty be ſo ſimple as to imagine the King my Maſter would give you Calais again?</hi>
                  </q> Which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101687:24"/>Anſwer touching her to the quick, ſhe demands <hi>Bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loigne</hi> in lieu of it. The King, who foreſaw the Conſequence of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſetting footing once more on <hi>French</hi> Ground, commanded her to be told, <q>
                     <hi>That he had rather the King of Spain ſhould give him a Box on the ear, than the Queen of England ſhould give him a Filip.</hi>
                  </q> And in troth ſhe had not <hi>Calais</hi> when the term of Eight Years was expired, although according to Treaty it was then to have been ſurrendred, or Hoſtages and ſufficient Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for payment of Five hundred thouſand Crowns promiſed her in caſe of Non-performance. But as uſual they fail of their Words, and the good Queen onely recovered Six ſcore thouſand Crowns at the Treaty of <hi>Troys.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Calais</hi> is once again become <hi>French. France</hi> loves her own Repoſe and Glory too much ever to part with it; and the Subjects as well as their Prince are too much in love with it, to ſuffer it ſlip out of their hands. I ſpeak but the very words of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal of <hi>Lorrain;</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>There is no Frenchman</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>but would rather hazard his Life, than adviſe the King to ſurrender Calais, and would not more willingly ſacrifice his whole Eſtate, than once give his conſent thereunto.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>This was ſpoken like a true <hi>Frenchman,</hi> and their Neigebours ſhould reſent ſuch daring Expreſſions as renderly as they themſelves do, if there be any thing of eredit in what <hi>S'aavedre</hi> reports, <q>
                     <hi>That the Prince's Acquiſts enhaunce his Dread and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101687:24"/>but what he forgoes redounds to his contempt and ſcorn.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Francis</hi> I. would never engage himſelf with <hi>Charles</hi> V. againſt <hi>England,</hi> fearing leſt in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of this Kingdom it ſhould happen to him as it did in the Conqueſt of <hi>Naples,</hi> between <hi>Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Arragon</hi> and <hi>Lowis</hi> XII. The Emperour being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to brook an Equal, and himſelf a Superiour. Beſides, <hi>Prancis</hi> ſhould have drawn upon himſelf a more potens Enemy, than him of whom he was rid: the Leopards of <hi>England</hi> being no leſs ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible than the Eagles of the Empire, or the Lions of <hi>Caſtile.</hi> Yea the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſtifly ſeconded the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in their demands of <hi>Calais,</hi> confeſſing, <q>
                     <hi>That they ought not to abandon them, and that if they were not protected, they very well knew Spain would be next ruin'd; ſo that their own Loſſes would be greateſt.</hi>
                  </q> This is written by the Cardinal of <hi>Lorrain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Spain</hi> then reaſon'd ſolidly and judiciouſly. In proſpect of this, <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. coined Medals of Gold, on whoſe Reverſe a Hand appeared out of a Cloud, holding a Pair of Balances <hi>in aequilibrio;</hi> the two Sodles whereof ſignified <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> with this Motto, <hi>He wins on whoſe ſide I turn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> governed her ſelf by the ſame Maxim, and aſſiſted <hi>Henry</hi> IV. ſo long as he was weakeſt, but ſeaſonably forbore when once ſhe ſaw him ſtart up beyond his juſt and proper bounds; and at that time told <hi>Sully,</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>That neither France nor England, nor any others, had any thing to do with the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101687:25"/>Low Countries; and that ſhe would never endure the French King ſhould gain ſo much as one inch of ground there.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And when as Pope <hi>Clement</hi> VIII. told Cardinal <hi>Oſſat,</hi> that <hi>England</hi> hated <hi>France</hi> implacably; he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, <q>
                     <hi>At this time England hates Spain more; and that they ought now to regard the preſent ſtate of Affairs, which had united both French and Engliſh againſt a common Enemy by one common Intereſt, which was evermore the ſtrongeſt and ſecureſt band among all States and Princes.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>This Reaſon which once ſerv'd the turn of <hi>France,</hi> ſhall at another opportunity do <hi>Spain</hi> a kindneſs; <q>
                     <hi>Becauſe Kingdoms are not to be reputed ſtrong or weak as they be in themſelves, but as they hold compariſon with their Neighbours, and from proportion wherewith they are adjuſted one unto another.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Du Pleſſis</hi> ſent this Meſſage to <hi>Walſingham</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> not to abandon <hi>Henry</hi> IV nor the <hi>German</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants. Let's ſee whether we may not uſe thoſe ſelf ſame words to evince the true Intereſt of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. Charles</hi> I. was convinc'd of it, and <hi>Charles</hi> II. hath been alſo, and will be poſſibly yet more, when like a great and deep Stateſman he ſhall be pleaſed to penetrate into the future. And it is not to be doubted, by the way he begins to take, and by what he had done formerly in Perſon at the Head of his Army, that he will not ſuffer himſelf to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reach'd by falſe Reaſonings, nor give his Slanderers occaſion to ſay of him as of his Grandfather King
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101687:25"/>
                  <hi>James,</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>That he knew not how, nor ever cared to manage buſineſſes, nor would once put his hands to diſpatch them, till ſuch time as both means and oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities had quite forſook him.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>I don't doubt but that <hi>Charles,</hi> our gracious King who now reigneth, will recollect what happen'd, how, and by whom, unto his Father; and what manner of Treatment he met with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in <hi>France,</hi> even with no leſs than Baniſhment. And for all poſſible Allurements from the <hi>French,</hi> he may be fully confident of receiving the ſame meaſure from them again, if the ſame occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were, which God forbid; or if he quit <hi>Spain</hi> with his own true Intereſt, and that of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which ſubſiſts by Commerce, to imbrace the Humours and Private Intereſt of half-ſighted and corrupt Miniſters. <hi>France</hi> debitting none other Commodities than her Brandies and Apiſh Gew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaws, in lieu of thoſe ſubſtantial Merchandizes <hi>England</hi> hath of her own, and importeth for all Quarters of the habitable World. And when Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alities are forſaken, and Deceits and Cheats taken, immoderate and reſtleſs Spirits do ordinarily take hold of ſuch ſenſible Arguments, to alienate and imbitter the Hearts of the People; which though frequently too too querimonious, yet gracious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces without humouring them in all their childiſh Cravings, will nevertheleſs comply with all that ſhall be manifeſtly for their ſolid Good.</p>
               <p>It were a pleaſant ſtory to relate the Civilities of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101687:26"/>
                  <hi>France</hi> to <hi>Edward</hi> IV. who being at a pinch, and driven out of his Kingdom by a Competitoy, and applying himſelf to one of their Kings for Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, could get none other Anſwer than this, <q>
                     <hi>That the League was made with the King of England and his State; but he being no longer King of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France could not without violating the Articles of that League imploy their Arms againſt him, who was then actually poſſeſſed of the Crown.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>They diſcharged themſelves of him very hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomly, and 'twas a ſine piece of Raillery. God forbid we ſhould be miſinterpreted to give theſe as ſawcy <hi>Omens,</hi> that which we give as plain and ſincere <hi>Items,</hi> not to rely upon the <hi>French</hi> Amity, which will prove a broken reed in caſe of need, as former and later Examples convince us. Yet this Fear is groundleſs in our days <hi>(thanks be to God)</hi> for <hi>Charles</hi> is a Prince ſo Auguſt, of ſo much Juſtice, and withall ſo well acquainted with the World as to that point, that he will not neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the Glory redounding to him from thoſe Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries he may atchieve with a wet Finger, by tread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Footſteps of his renowned Anceſtours. <q>
                     <hi>Above all it's then moſt needful to uſe ſuch means, when as a Sovereign Prince is grown ſo puiſſant by his Arms, that the progreſs of his Victories do make him terrible to his Neighbours.</hi>
                  </q> The Duke of <hi>Roan</hi> gives the ſame Advice in his <hi>Intereſt of Princes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:101687:26"/>
               <p>Thus I have endeavoured to lay open <hi>Monſieur</hi> and his Policies, if our Eyes will be but open to ſee 'em. And though we have propoſed ſuch ways and meaſures of attacquing the <hi>French</hi> in part of their own Dominions, which may not be deem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be at this Juncture ſo practicable, as if we ſhould rather go about to weaken 'em by help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Enemies and our Allies; yet that is an Exeoutive part, and fitter for other perſons to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and preſcribe. Our Deſign here being onely to make ſuch an Anſwer as we thought the fitteſt to brow-beat that domineering Nation; we judged that the apteſt and ſhorteſt way to refute their Contumelies and ſhallow Pretenſions on <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> was plainly to raiſe a Counter-battery of other Pretenſions on <hi>France,</hi> which are more grounded; to ſpeak to them like <hi>Britains,</hi> or old <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> to borrow ſome ſtrong Arguments <hi>ad hominem</hi> from both the <hi>Edwards</hi> Quiver, to manifeſt that we are not ſo weak as to ſtand a ſcanning it with 'em Scholar-like with a weak Pen; but rather Man-like to ſhew, that we are more ready to make an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer with our Swords, and with the point of it to prick this Bladder of Ambition, which ſo vainly puffs 'em up in conceit above their Neighbours, whom they ſo preſumptuouſly deſpiſe, ſlander, and would trample under; as if they forgot that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are the ſame when e're put to it, that they felt 'em to be at <hi>Poictiers,</hi> at <hi>Guyenne,</hi> and many other places in <hi>France,</hi> in the days of old.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:101687:27"/>
               <p>But if they or any of them in <hi>England</hi> will take offence at any thing that's ſaid here, we ſay 'tis but a Retaliation to their Writers. If they ſay, that their Writers ſpoke but their private ſenſe, then let this paſs for ſuch another piece. For I proteſt no publick or private perſon ever moved me to it, but the meer diſintereſted Affection I bear to my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; and I am ſo far from having any particular grudge againſt the <hi>French</hi> on any account, (ſuch as the Common People uſually have they know not why) that I declare they have been far more juſt and grateful to me than <hi>England</hi> it ſelf. But let that paſs; and if the <hi>French</hi> will or muſt own, that the <hi>French</hi> Politician, and theſe other Defamatory <hi>Memoirs,</hi> came from the Cloſet of publick perſons, and were ſpirited and are followed by ſuch in their preſent courſes; we <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> do likewiſe for our parts (whatever has been here ſaid by way of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and to ſhew <hi>Frenchmen</hi> that we want neither Eyes, Feeling, nor Courage) ſubmiſſively and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leave it to our Sovereign and his Counſellors, to return a more fit and publick Anſwer to <hi>France</hi> in this point in their own due time.</p>
               <p>For we are not unſenſible; that thoſe that ſit in eminent places have a larger and clearer proſpect of things than others; ſo that the word of Command and Motion is to be always expected from them as from the head: but ſometimes perſons that ſtand on a far lower ground may have a more particular knowledge of ſome Gaps and Precipices which are
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101687:27"/>juſt within their own reach and precinet. And even a Courrier or Scout may without reſlexion to his Generals, make a report touching the matters of fact he has obſerved in his courſe on the borders of the Enemy, and alſo what he thinks of their next Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, by what he hath heard or ſeen among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <p>☞ <hi>The</hi> Jeſuit<hi>'s Catchiſm, according to St.</hi> Ignatius Loyola, <hi>for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing and ſtrengthening of all thoſe which are weak in that Faith; wherein the impiety of their Principles, perniciouſneſs of their Doctrines, and iniquity of their Practices are declared. Printed for</hi> Robert Harford, <hi>at the</hi> Angel <hi>in</hi> Cornhil <hi>near the</hi> Royal Exchange, <hi>in Quarto. Price</hi> 1 s.</p>
            <p>☞ <hi>Humane Prudence, Or the Art by which a Man may raiſe Himſelf and Fortune to Grandeur. By</hi> A. B. <hi>Sold by</hi> Robert Harford, <hi>at the</hi> Angel <hi>in</hi> Cornhil. <hi>price</hi> 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
